OK.
Maybe we should get started.
This is the second of the post-training lectures,
so we're going to talk about the exciting developments in RLVR
or reinforcement learning from verifiable rewards.
And I think this is in some ways very timely.
I didn't get to update the slide,
but there was just an announcement by OpenAI folks
that they had solved one of the major problems.
So that's a MyOpenMath problem using
one of their thinking models.
How does that thing work?
That's exactly this thinking model stuff or RLVR stuff.
And so thus far, where we're at is we are at the left side here.
After we finished last lecture, we've got instruction tuning,
we've got RLHF, we've got some good stuff that's ChatGPT.
And what remains is the modern developments in thinking models.
The model's ability to do very long COT
and solve these hard, verifiable problems
like mathematics and coding in some cases as well.
And remember that I ended last lecture with this a little bit
of a downer note.
The RLHF wasn't really going to get us
where we wanted to go because of this problem called
overoptimization.
So we're going to go and collect a bunch of preference data.
Preference data is very useful.
We will build some reward model and then
we will RL against that reward model.
But this thing is fundamentally an annotation bottleneck
because we have a reward model and you
can't keep putting compute into the same reward model,
eventually you're going to overfit your reward model.
And no matter how good of a job you do at regularizing,
eventually you're going to run into this problem
with overfitting.
And so really, this is very depressing.
And it's not really the potential of reinforcement learning.
If you're a big reinforcement learning believer,
you're going to look at all things like AlphaGo
and so on, where you say, well, in these domains,
RL really did an amazing job.
What is the difference between what we're doing in RLHF
and what has been achieved in these more RL
native or RL natural domains?
And really the difference, I would say,
or one major difference between something like AlphaGo
and something like RLHF is that in AlphaGo, we are optimizing
exactly what we want.
You get the win-loss conditions of the game of Go.
You don't have any sloppiness to that definition.
And so you can just put in as much compute as you want.
And as long as the objective improves, you're doing well.
In some sense, these are search problems.
Whereas the top one is much more of a learning problem.
Not quite a precise distinction, but that's
one way of thinking about it.
So now there might be other domains like formal mathematics
or even natural language mathematics,
that have this flavor of being more verifiable and therefore
much more amenable to reinforcement learning.
So that's going to be the motivation for why we're
going to study some of these.
And the algorithms aren't going to be that different
fundamentally, but where we will end up
will actually be surprisingly different.
And so the lecture is going to be in two parts today.
This mirrors a lot of how we've structured
the course in other parts.
So in the first part of the lecture,
I'm going to talk about the core algorithms.
This is like basic knowledge for you all.
You will use some of this for your assignments.
And so I'm going to talk about things, what
is GRPO, how does PPO work.
And then after I've done that, I'm
going to dig through a bunch of open source releases
and show you how what I've taught you
in the first part reflects in the technical reports of many
of these major open source model releases.
So we're going to dive into the methods and basic section.
And the first thing that I'm going to start with is PPO.
We can't really discuss RL for language models
without discussing PPO.
And even though we've done it once,
PPO is confusing enough that I think you will
benefit from doing it twice.
The most important thing to identify,
let's say to remember in RL for language modeling, is
policy gradients.
And in particular this REINFORCE gradient trick.
Well, what we are always going to be doing is gradient descent
on our rewards.
And we are going to do so by taking essentially weighted SFT
updates.
The weights might be positive or negative.
We will define what R is.
But this equation is important because it will reappear
throughout this lecture.
This is in some sense the core from which
everything else is derived.
Now, building upon that, remember
that the intuition from last lecture
was we want to take more than one step at a time.
A policy gradient requires us to sample from our policy
every time we want to take a gradient step.
Can we reuse our rollouts?
Well, you can do TRPO.
You can do PPO and so on and so forth.
I'll talk about PPO in a minute.
And I've already talked about TRPO.
I won't really get too much into this.
If you've taken an RL course, PPO is, of course,
well understood to you, like you understand this algorithm,
but I don't assume that all of you have taken an RL class
and/or understand RL.
And so PPO, in case you're not familiar,
is a real workhorse of RL.
It's been used in a variety of very difficult RL settings.
OpenAI has done quite a few of these in their early days.
of being very RL pilled.
They had, this was I think, OpenAI
gym where they were talking about the PPO algorithm
and they're like, hey, we can get
these people to walk around using reinforcement learning.
In a much more dramatic demonstration of this
was their OpenAI bot, which they trained using PPO.
And so this can excel with deep RL
in high-dimensional action and state spaces,
where it's much more complicated to do RL than it is usually.
Oh, yeah.
And there's the OpenAI man running around.
All right.
So at a conceptual level, PPO is actually very simple.
Remember that I told you, an important part of all of this is getting rid of PPO.
That's been a motivating factor for a lot of people.
But if you look at the pseudocode of PPO,
this is from OpenAI's Spinning Up in RL documentation.
You look at this and you say, this is not that bad.
This is actually pretty easy.
I could implement this in one go.
You sample some trajectories.
I compute something called an advantage using any method
of advantage estimation.
I clip the advantage in this slightly strange but OK way.
And then I update the policy under this clipped advantage.
And that's fine.
And then I can fit something called a value function as well.
OK, fine.
This is all relatively easy looking in practice.
And so I think because of this, people are like, oh, it's OK.
PPO is totally fine.
But then you see blog posts that look like this,
and this should strike fear into your heart.
Because if you see a blog post that says the 37 implementation
details of PPO, you know that this is an algorithm that is very sensitive to your implementation
decisions.
And there's all sorts of things that you can do
and all sorts of different libraries and implementations,
and they give totally different numbers
based on which ones you use.
And it turns out that many people
have implemented this wrong.
And so there's a paper saying, like, actually
the baselines that some people use in PPO
aren't even baselines at all.
They fundamentally change the optimization problem.
And so basically because of this, I
think I would not be able to get through the rest of the lecture
without telling you, well, we actually
maybe need to start looking at some implementations of PPO.
And the implementations of PPO, let me tell you,
for language models are not particularly pleasant.
This is, I mean, a very good representative slide.
If anything, this is a very good description
of what PPO looks like.
You've got advantage estimation.
This big block in the middle, that's this advantage thing.
You've got an experience buffer because you're going
to keep some of the old stuff.
It's going to be training this value model.
And the value models are being used in the advantage estimation
calculation.
Notice how the green box appears twice.
And importantly, some parts of my objective, the KL term,
actually operate token by token.
So it's not actually just a bandit problem.
It's like a whole multi-step RL problem.
And this is all very difficult and complicated.
And so this has led to a variety of really tricky implementation
things that you have to do.
And if you look at a variety of implementations,
you find often that there are things
that people do for PPO that are a little bit strange and tricky
at times.
Let me see if I can find.
So one of my students implemented
a PPO for a project a while back doing RLHF.
So PPO, if you remember, was used in RLHF.
And so we had this nice robust reference implementation of PPO
and it took a long time to get working.
So I looked into the details, like what did we actually
do to get this thing to work.
The outer loop is fine.
The outer loop is something like you go through your rollouts
and you're going to take some PPO steps,
you're going to compute some loss and clip some gradients
and take some steps.
Totally reasonable outer loop.
But then you start looking into it.
For now, the actual inner compute loss part
follows almost exactly the PPO update.
So this also looks mostly good.
We're computing things like the advantages
and we're computing the clipping ratios.
And then we're updating the model based on that.
So this is all good.
But then you get to some of the messier parts.
Actually, I'll skip the rollouts,
where you have things like, well, maybe we
need KL penalties to keep the original model
close to the reference, but actually this
only works if you clip the KL off at 0, which of course,
if you know anything about KL divergences, that totally ruins
the point of a KL divergence.
You have both positive and negative values being summed.
If you remove this, it blows up immediately.
All things like this can happen.
This is not to say that this is the way you should implement PPO
if you were doing it.
I think the reason why I'm bringing this up
is to say implementations for RL algorithms can
be somewhat tricky and somewhat sensitive because of all
the moving pieces in PPO, and because
of the high variance in the gradient estimates.
These are all very, very tricky things that are happening.
And another thing that you often see,
this one is not just RL implementation.
It's very common.
In the original PPO paper, you have this thing
called a generalized advantage estimator that's basically
looking at this gamma discounted reward, where you have
this value function that's estimating
the reward at every token generation step.
But it turns out that people often just
use gamma equals lambda equals 1, which is just
a degenerate setting that turns this back into a bandit problem.
So you've thrown away a lot of the structure
that you get from PPO.
And so if you run this algorithm after a bunch of engineering,
you will get what you expect.
And when you run your RL algorithms for the assignment,
you should expect to see similar things, like the rewards go up.
The reward model rewards go up if you're doing RLHF,
and then the negative KL regularizers go down.
This is a reasonable thing to expect to see.
But anyway, the point of all of this is to say implementation of PPO can be quite painful.
Depending on the environment, it can require hacks to stabilize.
All of this is painful.
Not to say that it's not possible.
Lots of people have trained very good models on PPO.
Many of the labs have very turnkey solutions
for getting PPO to work at scale.
So this is not impossible.
But for people like researchers who are implementing this
from scratch, PPO can just be really finicky and complicated.
Another reason why PPO is disfavored in many cases
is that it requires a value model to estimate the value
at each token as you go.
And how big is the value model?
Well, it's as big as the original model,
so this consumes some memory that you would rather
be using for other stuff like models or inference servers.
So now you might say, well, in last lecture,
you told us about this DPO thing, and DPO seems pretty good.
Why don't we just use DPO for everything?
Well, the problem is DPO is a very specific solution
to a very specific problem.
DPO is good for pairwise feedback in the form
of Bradley-Terry comparisons.
That is very specific.
And if I want to solve math problems,
my math problems don't come in the form of inherently pairwise
comparisons.
There are other DPO variants that
are designed to break that pairwise structure,
but really you're just using the wrong hammer for the job.
You do not want to use DPO necessarily
for what you would normally use PPO for.
PPO is the more general hammer that you can hit everything
with.
DPO is generally offline.
Although I think this distinction
is very overstated because it can
be made online by just iterating DPO repeatedly.
So I don't think this is necessarily a big difference.
So that's the context for all of this.
And then so that similarly to DPO,
there's just an enormous desire by the research community
to not have to use PPO.
Hopefully, the fact that DPO and GRPO have gotten adoption
tells you how painful it was to get this to work in many cases.
And so GRPO much like DPO, is the alternative,
it is the simpler way to do RL for verifiable task.
It has taken over for the most part
RLVR in the open source, open knowledge,
let's call it community.
And it is very, very similar to PPO in spirit.
It just strips out a couple of the most complicated parts,
and by doing so, allows us to have a much simpler algorithm.
So GRPO is by DeepSeek paper.
I think it was there like DeepSeek math paper,
where you start with PPO.
It conceptually it says PPO is a good idea,
but we want to change just a few things.
And what does it change?
It changes arguably the most complicated and annoying part
of PPO, which is the value function.
So the value function is the thing
that you subtract as a baseline to reduce variance
of your gradient updates.
The value function is a whole neural network.
It destabilizes training.
We don't want the value network.
So what do we do?
Well, we get rid of the value network,
but we still need an advantage.
I don't want to do REINFORCE—
vanilla REINFORCE because the variance of that
is going to be really, really high.
So instead, what we're going to do
is I'm going to compute your advantage
as a z-score within a group, and I'll explain
what that means in a moment.
But basically, the idea is the following.
Normally, you look at a reward that you get
and if you had a value function, you would compare it
to your predicted value.
You would say, my neural network says,
I should have gotten a score of 5.
I got a score of 6.
So this is a good rollout.
That's usually what you do.
Instead, what you would do is you
would, let's say, your rollout with a score of 5.
You would now sample 10 other rollouts
and you would say, how good was I compared
to my 10 other rollouts.
If I'm doing better than my mean,
then I have a high advantage.
In some ways, a very natural way of computing advantage
in contexts where you can multiple sample
from the same prompt or something like that.
So GRPO is exactly this idea.
If you look at the initial definition of GRPO that
appeared in the DeepSeek paper, you see,
this is the objective that's being optimized.
They're going to do exactly the PPO update, where they have
this min clipped advantage, plus a KL term
to keep yourself close to the reference.
And then KL is computed in a particular way.
That detail is not particularly important.
And importantly, this advantage is
computed as a z-score over samples of a group of outputs,
o of 1 through o of G.
So that's-- or within each group, you have-- oh, sorry.
This advantage of i, this is the place where
you compute the advantage.
What you do is you take the reward over your rollouts
within each group, you subtract the mean and you divide by the standard deviation.
So you get a z-score for each group.
So in the online case and this is an important distinction
because in many cases, you may actually
end up running this online rather than offline.
In the online case, the clipping just
disappears because the ratio between pi theta old and pi
theta is 1, this clipping operator never does anything
and you just get min A of i, A of i.
So this is just advantage minus a KL penalty.
So I'm going to do RL on my advantage, which
is defined by this.
So in the online rollout case, it
is a very, very simple object that makes sense as RL target.
So I can pause here for a moment in case
any of the conceptual bits of GRPO are not clear.
I mean, in some sense, this is the foundation of all
of the exciting math stuff.
Or you can replicate all of the exciting math stuff using GRPO.
So it's worth understanding in a little bit of detail
before we move on to some of the nitty-gritty details.
OK.
Good.
Simple enough that everyone understands in one go.
I will take it.
And GRPO is very, very simple because of the lack of value
function, you can basically write down all of GRPO
in a very simple block of code, where you just say,
I'm going to roll out k times, I'm
going to compare my observed rollout to those k references,
z-score it and then just take a reinforced gradient
against those weights.
So you will write this in your assignment.
And it's going to involve a very simple set of steps.
Compute a reward for each of your k rollouts.
Normalize your rollouts, compute the KL term.
And then just take gradient updates
on the combination of your KL term and these rollouts.
You'll have to do a little bit of thinking because in order
to do this using autodiff, you will have
to do a stop grad somewhere.
But it's actually not that complicated.
And you can see that you can do a one-page implementation
of this basic idea.
And this is a reference implementation of GRPO
that I took from some folks at McGill,
which has a really nice little toy version of this whole thing.
And the computation of the group indices,
and the standard deviation calculation and all of that
just fits in one half of a slide.
The only thing that they do differently
than the literal paper write up of GRPO
here is they add a little tiny weeny negative 4
to the standard deviation calculation
to prevent it from blowing up when you only
have a single sample, or if your samples happen
to have the exact same rewards, which does happen if you're
in a domain where you can get exactly numerically 0 rewards,
like you failed to solve a math problem.
But hopefully, this emphasizes to you
how straightforward GRPO is, and why almost all open source
work has been built on this algorithm.
It's easy to implement, easy to understand.
And if you, as we'll see in the results,
it provides fairly compelling results
in terms of emulating a lot of what the closed source labs have
done using potentially PPO.
So how well does it work?
In the original DeepSeek math paper,
which if you're into math AI stuff,
I would encourage you to read, it's
a nice and really interesting set of results.
They show that GRPO, the yellow and the blue lines,
does much better than RFT, like rejection fine-tuning.
You'll implement this as a baseline as well.
That's just taking the correct answers
that your model generates and training on them
and throwing away everything else.
And they seem to show process supervision, which
is grading not just the final answer,
but grading the intermediates gives you some gains.
I'll talk more about that later.
That is an important thing to discuss and cover
because that's one of the big design decisions
for these kinds of RL problems.
But for now, you can just internalize the fact
that GRPO works.
The blue and yellow lines are above the others.
OK.
So now let's think a little bit more about the GRPO objective.
What is happening in this objective?
Are we actually taking policy gradients?
There are important conceptual questions that we should really
think through.
And so if we think about the difference between GRPO and PPO,
remember that PPO had this value function thing which
feeds into the advantage.
And in GRPO, we strip that out and we replace
that with the z-score guy.
This A of i, ratio of r minus mean
divided by standard deviation.
So is this a good advantage?
I think for those of you that have been in an RL class,
you already know the answer to this question.
Is this a good advantage function?
What makes a good advantage?
What makes a valid advantage function?
Well, if you look at Sutton and Barto, the big classic book
for reinforcement learning they will say,
well, there's this algorithm called REINFORCE with baseline.
And the things you're allowed to do
is that if you're doing policy gradients, which
is this line over here, this very first equation.
I want to take my gradient step in the direction of my rewards.
And the thing you can do is you can take your rewards
and I can subtract any—what they
call state-dependent baseline, in this case, our state.
If we're in the bandit world, it's just the prompt.
So you can have a prompt-dependent baseline
that you can subtract.
And anything that does just this is a valid form
of a policy gradient.
So you're still going to descend in the same direction
as long as you do this.
And depending on your choice of b,
you will either have lower or higher variance
in doing this gradient descent process.
Now, you should probably notice that what we're doing
is not this.
We are not just subtracting a constant value,
we are also dividing by the standard deviation.
And so that is a problem.
It turns out well, it's in some ways a problem.
In other ways, it's not.
If you really want a conceptually clear algorithm
that really does what's written on the tin,
it actually descends the reward.
GRPO does not do that.
Because as I've highlighted in red here,
GRPO divides by the standard deviation, which
breaks this baseline contract.
We're not just dividing or subtracting a baseline.
We're also normalizing by the standard deviation
of my rewards.
Of course, there's another thing that GRPO does,
which I didn't mention earlier.
As an implementation detail that is tricky, which is GRPO
does this almost per token.
So they'll divide by the total length of the sequence
as a normalization factor.
But if you try to derive GRPO from first principles,
following the policy gradient and baseline theorems,
you'll end up with something different.
You won't have a length normalizer
and you won't have the standard deviation normalization.
And some folks soon after GRPO came out noticed this,
and they wrote a paper basically saying, well,
if you don't do these two things that are different,
then you get very different potentially very
positive behavior.
I will talk about that.
Also, when we get to the--
not OpenAI, sorry DeepSeek R1 paper.
But the main thing here is to say
GRPO is not the first principles derivation of this idea.
It is actually doing something slightly different
with both pros and cons.
So what are these two terms doing?
We know that GRPO is not actually directly descending
on the reward objective.
We know that it has these two correction factors.
What do they do?
Well, the length normalization is easier to see.
So what are we doing?
We are dividing longer sequences with a bigger number.
And so what this will do is that it's
going to encourage the model to generate
long outputs because-- or sorry when you're wrong
it will encourage you to generate wrong outputs.
Because let's say-- I know that I'm going
to get a math proof wrong.
I'm going to incur my negative reward of let's say, negative 1.
I'm just going to generate an infinitely long string.
If I do that, I'll get to divide by infinity,
and I'll get to totally get rid of my negative penalty.
That's an extreme case.
But you understand that if you divide by the output,
you encourage the model to blab on once it realizes that it
cannot actually solve the problem.
So this is a length problem that you end up getting.
If you fix that, you'll find that often
what people have observed in GRPO COT, like chain of thought,
thinking length growing and growing and growing,
that actually turns out to just cap off at a constant
rather than just continually and forever grow.
So this seems like a potentially good thing.
And especially on the incorrect cases,
you really don't want to be generating longer
and longer and longer outputs.
So the standard deviation normalization,
this one's a little bit more complicated.
But if you think about it, what I'm doing
is I'm dividing by the standard deviation.
And so this can be thought of as emphasizing
problems where the standard deviation is small.
And when is my standard deviation
small for a binary reward problem?
Well, that's when the problems are too easy or too hard.
If my problem is really easy and I get 100% all the time,
I'm going to divide by 1 over or the number--
I'm going to divide by basically 0
because there's 0 variation if I always get a question correct.
Similarly, if I always get a question wrong,
I have 0 variation in my rewards.
I'm going to upweight that significantly.
So the standard deviation term is upweighting the two sides,
both easy and hard questions.
That seems like clearly a thing that maybe we
don't want because we want our models to potentially learn
on things that are within its solvability range.
So that's the algorithmic components of RLVR.
And I'm going to go through several
of the different recent model releases
and talk through all the algorithmic components
that I think are quite important, including some
of the stuff that I added this year that's new, which is really
the agentic stuff that I think has been catching on
and is increasingly important for using and deploying
these models.
But before I do that, I can pause here
and if anyone has algorithmic questions,
I'll take them before I move on.
OK.
Good.
All right.
So we're going to start with DeepSeek R1
because I think this is a bit of a social phenomenon.
I think everyone should know a bunch about DeepSeek R1.
I think it's a lovely paper kicked off
the wave of open source RLVR models.
And what's remarkable about it, I
think it was really the first thing
to have matched OpenAI O1's behavior.
So the key things about OpenAI O1
was you have very long chains of thought.
It's clearly RL, and you have really good performance
on hard math problems.
And they also provided RL recipe that anyone could do.
And I think from the perspective of R&D, this is very important.
If your solution was like you have this horrible PPO
thing that no one but DeepSeek can run,
then that is much less of an impact, at least for us
researchers than this kind of GRPO thing,
which anyone can really play with, even you
in your assignments.
And finally, they have some really interesting distillation
insights that I think have held up even now.
So the starting point of DeepSeek R1, and I
think you can see how a lot of DeepSeek's expertise
build on each other.
So they had this DeepSeek math paper,
where they were doing GRPO.
They had already understood a lot of the nuances of RL
on math problems.
And so because of this, they started off
with a lot of the components of DeepSeek math.
But one of the really important differences, and I'll
highlight an expert just because I
think it's particularly important is they abandon
process supervision, which was the thing that worked really
well in DeepSeekMath, and they go only
with outcome supervision.
And just to be clear, outcome supervision
is when you have reward only for whether the final answer is
correct or incorrect.
And process supervision is when you have a grading rubric, let's
say, to check the validity of intermediate steps in a proof.
A lot of people thought process supervision was important.
Turned out it wasn't critical for a lot of things.
So R1 was interesting in that it has
a lot of different components.
But one of the very interesting components
is R1 zero, where they don't really
do that much post-training, so they have a base model.
Of course, the base model, as we all now
is also [? MIT ?] trained.
And so this guy can do some amount of instruction following.
And then on top of this base model,
they do basically RLVR, where the rewards for their GRPO
algorithm is accuracy, rewards for whether they correctly
solve a collection of math problems and format rewards.
And this one is important because the format rewards
basically allow them to strip out the chain of thought later.
They want the model to properly use
thinking tags to enclose their COT.
But this is a very simple recipe.
GRPO is very simple.
Accuracy rewards are very simple.
In fact, you will implement and replicate
essentially the set of results in some ways,
and you do just this very simple recipe.
And where do you end up?
Well, you end up something that is only a little bit worse
than OpenAI O1.
So this is really, really, really clean.
And I like this result because it
has none of the messes of a real production post-training
pipeline thrown in.
You don't really question whether oh,
was it because of the RLHF helping or this or that.
It's a very simple base model plus GRPO.
Your math abilities are quite good.
And I think R1 also took off, partially
because of the interesting phenomena
they claim to have observed in the paper.
So one of the things they claim to have observed
is as we go longer and longer and longer
during training, the model is able to think for longer
and longer and longer.
Their COT get longer and longer and longer.
And they also highlighted this thing that I believe
went viral on social media, which is like the aha moment,
where the model is if you train it for enough,
its COT is able to do things like,
oh, there's an aha moment that I can flag here.
And they thought this was really interesting.
It is unclear to me whether either of these phenomena
are really particularly impressive in many ways.
We now know that longer CoTs is arguably a natural side
effect of the length normalization of the GRPO algorithm.
And the aha moment others have showed
is actually appears in even the base model.
And so clearly, it can't just be a result of the RL algorithm.
Lots of people say aha, I can use this
as part of solving the math problem.
The model has learned it during pre-training.
It's not surprising at all that somehow during RL
just happens to get extracted because it's
emitting a lot of math tokens.
So I think the phenomena that was highlighted
is not particularly salient or exciting,
but I do think R1 was a really important milestone in that it
highlighted just how simple RLVR could be.
This is very, in some sense clean as an algorithm
and as a way of solving these really difficult problems.
And so R1 zero was this very nice, clean controlled setting.
And then R1 was their attempt to productionize this system.
And I think one thing that's nice about R1
and I'll show you the Qwen equivalent
later, is you can see how you stack all the pieces together.
I think we've studied all the pieces in isolation.
We know where pre-training is.
We know that there's RLHF, we know SFT,
but how do we compose all of the pieces
to actually get a system at the end?
Well, usually the thing that you do is something like,
well, we have our mid-trained model,
we're going to do a bunch of reasoning training, maybe
some long context extension somewhere too.
And then we're going to do RLHF at the end,
because that's in some sense, the most user-facing object.
We want to make sure that the formatting and all of this is nice.
RLHF can very much help with that process.
One of the other things that they did was they
added a language consistency reward for the chain of thought
for their production model.
I think if I remember the report right,
this was because the R1 zero style
training without a consistency reward
would language switch in COT, and they
thought this was very uninterpretable and slightly
disturbing.
And so they wanted to just have it output
a single consistent language.
And so they do this just for interpretability reasons.
And then they have some of the non-verifiable rewards
as well, thrown in to GRPO, almost
as blending into the RLHF process,
but otherwise it's a very, very similar thing.
And the whole pipeline, I think, is very straightforward.
So for SFT, what they do is pretty simple.
So in R1 zero, they don't want to do any SFT at all.
But in R1, they're willing to do long COT data.
And when you're reading these open source tech reports,
it's fun to try to read between the lines.
When they say something like, we construct
and collect a small amount of long COT data,
you might wonder--
I wonder if that was distilled from some other models.
That is a particularly, like, negative thing
for open source models.
Everyone is nowadays doing this, but I just find it funny
that it's very carefully written to collect a small amount
of long COT data.
And so this is used to fine-tune the model.
We know that for a very good base model, just SFT on long COT
can unlock a lot of O1-style capabilities.
And that's a great starting point for RL.
So they start there and then they add some verification
to filter out the CoTs.
And then they continue on with processing.
And I think many papers since then,
some including some from my students
have shown things that if you have
the right kind of distillation procedure
and you have the right kinds of base model,
you can basically get a lot of the long COT reasoning juice
just from SFT.
And I think this is maybe interesting
because one of the things that I think
is still an open question is, do you really
need RL for some of this?
And I think maybe one way of thinking about the role of RL
in language modeling is that RL is
a great source of supervision.
If you're solving frontier math problems,
you just don't have the supervision
to get detailed long CoTs, and RL allows
you to self-generate that.
But once someone has generated these long CoTs,
you could potentially also learn from imitation.
And that seems to be what a lot of these distillation results
partially show.
So the RL part for R1 is basically the same as R1 zero.
Minus the language consistency loss that I mentioned,
it's basically just we run the RL training using GRPO.
And that leads to essentially the final phase,
which is what we learned about last lecture.
So we do some basic instruction tuning style SFT and then RLHF.
For non-verifiable tasks, they basically use the same thing
as DeepSeek V3.
So there's really no surprises at all here.
How well does it work?
It's really, really good.
And I think this is the reason why there was all
that panic or big noticing of DeepSeek
because R1 was genuinely a very good model.
It beat O1 on many of the categories.
It matched a lot of the test time scaling behavior
that people expected.
And it came from a very simple recipe.
So it was very easy to understand where
the gains were coming from.
And the last thing related to some of the distillation
discussions that I was saying is you can then take R1's CoTs
and you could put it into Qwen 2.5,
and if you did so, you could really significantly boost
the performance of these models.
In some cases, matching a lot of these specialized thinking
models.
And so in other words, really, if you
can get the right kinds of long CoTs
that are legible to these models,
often it is possible to get them to reason
for long periods of time, like the base models are already
surprisingly good, and this works even for Llama models
as well, which I think is quite fascinating.
So to close out the DeepSeek saga,
I quite liked a lot of the DeepSeek tech reports,
because they often do both ablations
and they also tell you failed things that didn't work.
And if you've been following what they've been doing,
DeepSeekMath has all of this process reward model stuff.
It's like we got to verify all the steps
and then you read R1 and you say where did the process reward
models go.
Well, they tell you where the process reward models go,
which is we tried to get process reward models to work.
They just didn't do very much for us.
It turns out that outcome reward models are great
and they're good enough.
And you can scale the data for those a lot better.
I think a big debate for PRMs was,
where are you going to get these step-by-step rubrics.
And it's very hard to scale that up.
I think at this point, it's quite clear now
that outcome reward models are very, very good.
And that's the bulk of where the action is happening.
Similarly, if you were around for the initial O1 release,
a lot of people speculated about what was going on
inside OpenAI's O1.
They were like, oh, are they doing PRMs?
Are they doing tree search like AlphaGo?
They tried a lot of MCTS and they
describe we couldn't get it to work very well.
I just very much want to highlight
the fact that they're very open about all
these explorations and the things that they tried
and didn't work, rather than to say they didn't try it at all.
Cool.
All right.
And if I talk about--
or actually, I'll pause here in case anyone
has questions, although I don't know if-- yeah.
you should explain the positive reward basis
by Because I thought you said for negative,
like we encourage to divide by infinity and 0
for positive.
Yeah.
So the question was like for positive cases
what the length normalizer do.
And of course, in those cases, the length normalizer
encourages you to shorten the COT, which is good
if you want to save on inference costs,
bad if that degrades your accuracy.
But I think the main issue is that for the long--
for the negative ones, you get some really long responses
and the positive cases, it can't shrink it
that much because there's a lower bound to how small
your COT can go to solve a particular problem.
I guess I'm trying to understand that explanation
for the diagram.
Is that--I think Doctor GRPO has a cleaner diagram of this.
So in the R1 diagram, this is all aggregated.
This is all of the responses across their evals.
It's not just the positive ones.
But if we look at the Doctor GRPO plot over here.
So this is like the average output length and this is the incorrect output length.
And so you see that the correct output length is here.
So you see somewhat that this is really
being driven by the incorrect ones
as we would expect from the explanation.
So the story, at least in these sets of controlled comparisons,
is quite clean and clear.
Yeah.
Cool.
So now, I'm also going to talk about an alternative method,
Kimi K1.5 or alternative paper and approach.
And I always feel like when I talk about R1,
I'm obligated to talk about Kimi K1.5 because they came out
at the same time as R1.
They also beat R1, and yet everyone is all about DeepSeek,
and Kimi is not quite as often brought up in the conversation,
even though their models are extremely good.
And I'm not just talking about them out of pity, per se.
I think Kimi has this nice thing that they do something--
some sets of things, quite differently than DeepSeek,
and we can learn quite a bit from the fact that both
of these work.
I think this is part of the theme of this class, which
is by reading all of these technical reports
and by looking at broader patterns,
we can roughly start to understand
what are the valid or easy spaces to get
these algorithms to work.
So they do actually quite a bit more
detail in talking about the dataset construction and curriculum
generation for the RL process, which many have said
is quite important.
And they also have a different RL algorithm,
which in some ways, has similar intuitions
but is not exactly GRPO.
And so this is another nice validation that technically
speaking, I don't think you necessarily
need something like GRPO to get these guys to work.
So the first part I want to talk about is the data.
The data remains very important for all of these processes.
And for RL, there's an additional wrinkle
of curriculum, what difficulties of problems
do you want to throw in?
In SFT, you don't really think about difficulty
very much because you just jam the data in there.
For whatever data that you want, you just
do pre-training losses and the model
is forced to learn from these.
In SFT, there's a little bit more of a subtlety.
We talked quite a bit about the hallucination issues,
and maybe sometimes you don't want
to train on some of this data.
But for RL, there's this additional wrinkle
that if your problems are too hard, you get no rewards.
And if you get no rewards, you have no signal.
And if you have no signal, you can't learn.
So it's very important to have broad coverage
of the right kinds of examples.
And so what the Kimi folks do is first of all,
they try to get a whole big, broad range of coverage of data.
Unsurprising, they exclude multiple choice
because that's covered in lots of different domains.
They want things that require long, deep thought.
And their argument is maybe multiple choice
doesn't have that.
But maybe this last one I think is maybe
the most important idea.
This appears in a lot of different RL papers.
You basically filter all the examples for things
that either pass, or sorry, you filter them
based on a best of k filter.
So here you take examples.
And if they succeed on best of 8,
if you sample eight times and the model
可以在至少一次的情况下做到，那这并不是一个好的RL示例，
因为它已经处于模型能力的边缘。
你不会教给它任何特别新的东西。
所以你只看那些基本无法通过这个测试的示例，
因为这让我们能够基本上挑选
合适类型的问题。
这样就能节省计算资源。
它让你可以完全跳过某些问题。
你也可以在两边都进行过滤
以获得既不太难也不太容易的问题。
我认为研究界的普遍共识是
进行这种中等难度范围的过滤
是非常好的，如果你真正想要的是
让RL以稳定的步伐进步。
和DeepSeek一样，没有关于SFT的描述。
我们可以推测那是什么，
但我们没有具体的信息。
所以我认为Kimi有趣的地方在于
他们有一个受DPO启发的论点，
但他们最终实际上到达了一个
与GRPO非常相似的地方。
而且我认为，他们最终到达相似的地方这一事实
暗示了在这些组件中哪些
在你设计新的RL算法时可能是有用的，
比如说。
所以他们和所有人从完全相同的地方开始。
所以这现在对你们所有人来说应该看起来很熟悉。
它只是在我的策略下最大化期望奖励。
并且我在右边有这个KL正则化项，它
让我靠近我的基础策略，或者也许
甚至是之前迭代的策略，
取决于你打算如何做这个——做这个RL。
所以他们将遵循相同的DPO风格推导，其中
他们说假设我可以解析地最大化
然后我求解出奖励模型，它
做到了那个最大化，或者对应于那个最大化。
那将给我这个策略的比率。
然后我将把它代回上面的目标函数中
并尝试求解正在发生什么。
好吧，他们现在说的是他们
want to try to match the reward model.
And for this equality to be— they
want this equality to be true, which is true at the minimizer.
And therefore, this is a big heuristic.
If something's equal at the minimizer,
why don't we just put a squared loss on that thing
and minimize the squared loss?
I think optimization people looking at this
would be horrified at this, but I
think this is a totally reasonable intuition in some ways.
We know that these two things should be close
when the model is good.
So it is also maybe OK to treat making those two
things explicitly close as a surrogate.
This derivation, as you can see, is very, very different
from GRPO.
We're not going through the PPO path to derive this update.
But now, actually, lo and behold,
you take a gradient of this L, you
end up with something that looks surprisingly like GRPO
with an added regularizer term.
What you end up with is this thing
that is a policy gradient with a baseline R bar.
And that R bar is actually the mean of each condition,
these x's.
And you have this additional regularizer term,
which is essentially the KL term that would appear in GRPO.
So in some sense, we've reinvented
the group mean normalized baseline
through quite different means.
And so the Kimi folks I think in some ways
had a nicer or better view of the length problem.
I think the GRPO folks were like,
isn't it great that the length is growing uncontrollably.
I'm sure our model is being smarter.
That's a little bit of an uncharitable take,
but when you present this plot as a positive thing,
the implied statement is like, it's great
that our model is thinking for longer.
But the Kimi folks look at this long COT problem
and they say, well, if we're making long CoTs potentially,
that's very wasteful.
We don't really want long CoTs because CoTs cost inference.
So not only do they not have a length problem,
because if you look at this objective,
they don't normalize by sequence length,
but they actually want to go even further
and they want to compress the length of the response.
And this is another important feature
that we see generally occurring in language model development.
We want the CoTs to be as short as possible.
We want to solve hard problems.
We don't want to think for very long,
because when we think for very long,
we have to essentially subsidize the user.
If you're OpenAI and your users have the $200 Pro Plan,
and your models are thinking for an hour
at a time, that's not a very good place to be in.
Whereas if your models are thinking
for five minutes at a time, that is a great place to be in.
And so for all of these reasons, Kimi
wants to go and compress the CoTs.
How do you do that?
Well, the simplest thing to do
is you come up with a heuristic length reward
and you just tack it on to the RL process.
This reward is surprisingly complicated.
And the thing that they're doing is
you're trying to make longer sequences shorter and shorter.
Correct answers also should be short.
The interesting balance here is if you
make the incorrect answers too short,
they no longer have a way to recover.
So let me give you an example.
Imagine I'm bad at geometry.
AI bad at geometry, I get lots of incorrect answers,
and the penalty makes my geometry CoTs really short.
Now, my geometry CoTs are 0.
I'm really bad at geometry.
I will never recover from this.
I will never get a positive geometry reward ever again.
And I'm stuck.
And so what you do is you don't force the incorrect answers
to be super short.
You incentivize them to be just a little bit shorter
than the average, so that the incorrect stuff
doesn't grow unboundedly.
And so this has, in the end, a surprisingly reasonable set
of outcomes.
And so as I said before, they have a really nice RL set
of views on how they do their data set curation.
So not only do they have this data set that they filter,
they also look at the success rates
of how often they're able to solve particular problems.
And once the model masters a particular problem,
it gets taken out of the problem set.
So you save some compute doing that.
I think basically everyone doing RL does these success rate
filtering to avoid both wasting compute
or working on problems that are way too hard for the model.
And they basically have rewards that, for code, they
take ground truth solutions and they generate some new test
cases.
And for math, they actually have a reward model
to check for answer equivalence checks.
And this is a really funny thing in some ways,
because we started out this lecture
by saying we want to work on formal math or something,
something truly verifiable, where you can--
a compiler can check the correctness of your math.
And then we've gone through most of the lecture.
And then in the end, where did we end up?
Well, we ended up with a reward model,
a reward model that checks the correctness of math answers.
Once again, you'll see why in the assignment
or maybe if you play with the assignment, you'll see why.
You'll quickly find out that answer equivalence checking
is a very difficult problem.
Because in math, you can write equivalent things in many ways.
And not only that, a language model
can give the answer back in many ways.
Even if you prompt it to say give the answer back
in LaTeX boxed, maybe sometimes it skips the boxed,
maybe add some extra stuff to the box.
There are lots of ways that the model can just
fail to get the right answer by a strict correctness checker,
even though it has the right idea.
And so for these reasons, basically, most RL projects
have a very complicated answer checker, either a regex
or a model, or who knows what in order
to avoid these kinds of problems.
It's a real rabbit hole getting the verified part of RLVR.
Cool.
The last thing which connects to some of the systems bits
that we had talked about earlier and the inference bits
is RL optimization.
And RL infra is really quite hard.
Training is hard and inference is hard.
And RL puts the two together.
So in some ways, no wonder it is really horrible and difficult.
Even worse, I think one of the things that you don't initially
appreciate about how hard it is to make RL efficient
is think of the following scenario.
Now, imagine you've got your rollouts,
but you've got one really hard math problem,
let's say one of them is like the Riemann hypothesis.
And your model is really chugging along
on the Riemann hypothesis.
It's got this gigantic COT.
Now, what's happening?
In the meantime, if you're doing naive inference,
everyone else is waiting on this one rollout
to complete in order to move on to the next phase.
So if you're doing these batch things,
long rollouts can really hurt you.
And so RL really needs to deal with all of these really
tricky low-level details.
So you need to deal with the fact
that some CoTs can get really long.
Do you need to truncate them, do you somehow
set them into a different machine, who knows?
These are all decisions that you can make.
If you switch from training to rollouts, you roll out once
and then you train and you roll out and you train,
you have to somehow deal with this.
Either some of your machines are pure rollout machines,
and some of them are training machines,
or you're switching out frameworks all the time.
Both of them are very costly.
And then finally, you have this really difficult and horrible
trade off, which is on-policy stuff is mathematically
and training dynamics wise very nice.
So GRPO in its simple on-policy form behaves very nicely.
You will experience this in your assignments
and then you will get greedy.
You will say but my systems utilization is so low.
I could do so much better if only I could reuse my rollouts,
then I can overlap my inference and computation
and do all clever things.
And so you will attempt to reuse these rollouts.
And that will lead to off-policy problems which
then lead to destabilizing your training
and all sorts of things that are very difficult.
So these are all sorts of things that end up
getting very, very tricky.
And so I think most open source technical reports will
have these days a section talking about their RL infra,
and their RL infra is going to have both a training part.
That's the blue boxes over here and an inference part, which
is the green part on the right.
And you're going to have to move weights from the training part
to the inference part.
So you need some sort of story for how to move those around.
And you need to coordinate them closely.
And in some cases, maybe they even
share the same machines because as inference is running,
the training one might be idle.
So all of these are complexities.
And you have lots of very complicated systems things to do.
So we already know that Kimi beats OpenAI O1,
but we also see some really nice things
showing that as RL proceeds, you're able to think longer
and performance goes up.
But in some cases, it's not that we're just
unboundedly increasing tokens.
We end up getting cases where I think
OmniMath is a good example.
You're not thinking for that much longer,
but your performance continues to go up.
So maybe this is a good example of this length control kicking
in and doing good things.
The final thing I want to talk about is you might wonder,
is this actual RL stuff much better
than just training on correct answers.
This is called expert iteration.
It worked very well in a number of past papers.
In cases where you're dealing with very unstable stuff,
you may actually want to do expert iteration instead.
Kimi K1 has very large scale ablations
showing that these kinds of RL methods
work consistently better than expert iteration.
So that's the orange beating the blue over here.
So you can't really avoid RL if you want to squeeze out
all of your performance.
I can pause here in case anyone has
questions about the Kimi stuff.
And then I'll move on to the last of the three
which is Qwen 3.
Great.
OK.
So the last one that I want to talk about is Qwen 3 and also
Qwen 3.5-Next-Coder.
The names are getting complicated.
And Qwen 3 is later.
But they have actually really interesting scaling and data
results.
So I want to talk about those.
And the successor to this, which is Qwen 3.5-Next-Coder is
interesting because I think has the most details of I would say
agentic RLVR training out of the major technical reports and they do
lots of cool things.
So once again, as with DeepSeek, one
of the nice things that we see with the Qwen report
is the full way that all of these are organized.
And this is very similar to the DeepSeek structure.
We do base model to basically SFT, then reasoning RL.
And then they have this thinking mode fusion.
I'll talk about that later.
And then they do RLHF and then they
have a model that gets shipped.
But of course, they don't want to serve that directly.
So they do distillation to get their smaller models.
I mean, Qwen 3 is quite a respectable open source model.
You can basically have this be your mental picture of how
frontier-ish language models are built, putting
all the components together.
And I think you would have a pretty reasonable picture
of what is happening.
And Qwen uses basically, at this point, tried and tested
playbook for RLVR.
I think they take lots of the best parts of Kimi and DeepSeek,
and they get it right.
They do a lot of filtering for difficulty because we
know that saves compute.
That's a good way to get good data.
They also do other things, like they remove things
that the model can get right without COT
because we know that's not a thinking problem.
They remove things that are too similar to validation data
to try to decontaminate things.
And then they do a little bit of manual filtering
on reference CoTs.
Maybe most remarkably about Qwen 3 is they actually do their RL
on very few examples, just 4,000 examples.
But once again, if you have the rest of the pipeline right,
you can actually get surprisingly far.
So the core of the RLVR components
are maybe not super surprising because they are really
building off of DeepSeek R1 and also Kimi.
There are some interesting Qwen 3 specific things, some of which
they've ended up getting rid of, but I think some of the ideas
are actually quite interesting.
So one of the things that they do
is they mix thinking and non-thinking things with tags.
And that's how they end up having a thinking mode, where
the model has a long COT and they can mix
that with a non-thinking mode.
So both the instant response model and the long COT model
basically live in the same model.
This was not true in many cases.
There was often a thinking mode and a non-thinking model,
even at OpenAI.
They also have--I thought this was quite interesting,
which is they have this way of early exiting thinking where
if they append a special string, they'll immediately stop the COT
and the model is forced to give an answer to whatever prompt
is given.
We see this even in-- we see this affordance in interfaces
like ChatGPT, where you're able to terminate the thinking early
and try to get an immediate answer, for example.
But what we see with this and I've always
thought this was a surprising and interesting thing, which
is that as you vary the thinking budget, doing
this early termination trick, you end up
finding that the performance of the model
degrades gracefully, even though at the lower-thinking budgets,
these models are kind of getting truncated mid-thought,
they're able to give surprisingly reasonable
responses even at that point.
And we see that consistently, even
with very small-thinking budgets, the thinking
mode models are much better on all
of these mathematical or coding tasks
compared to the instant response mode, which
is much more of the classic instruction following plus RLHF
models.
And so you can-- one of the nice things they do for us is look
at the contribution of all of the different components
to performance.
And in many ways, this is not something that
shouldn't surprise you too much.
If you do this reasoning RL and then general RL,
you're able to slowly get improvements
in all of the different tasks, things like Arena-Hard
or CounterFactQA.
These are general tasks for which you want more normal RL,
and we see significant boosts to that performance
across the board.
There are some degradations that we see in math and coding
because we fuse together non-thinking components,
but the degradation is not so bad.
I think, actually, even though these numbers
in an absolute sense are small in later releases,
I think in some of the Qwen 3.5, they've
gone back on fusing both thinking
and non-thinking into a single model.
I think what-- they used to call these hybrid models because they
found this drop unacceptable.
They wanted to squeeze out all the juice
possible on thinking modes.
And so they've now, I think, separated
these models from each other.
The very last topic and paper that I want to cover is Qwen 3--
or sorry, I flipped the two.
It's Coder-Next not Next-Coder, which is one of the newer models
to come out.
And I think if you're interested in general agent
stuff, of course, there's other agent things
to think about, harnesses.
But if you're interested in how do you actually build an agent,
This is probably a good report to go read.
Qwen3-Coder-Next great agent post-training paper.
But in some ways, post-training for an agent
is not very different from everything that we've described.
It's not like there's a new agent training algorithm.
Really, you should internalize this lesson
throughout the entire class.
Data is the important thing.
So if you're going to train an agent or post-training an agent,
what are you going to do?
You're going to get the data together.
So there's two parts to the data.
To get a lot of the capabilities,
you can't just inject them at the end.
You have to probably start a little bit earlier.
And so there's an extensive mid-training phase
that happens to try to get as much coding
and agent-like capabilities into the model as possible.
So they'll do things like they'll
take repositories and concatenate the files
in the repository to generate these very long context data
and put it into the model.
We know that the model is eventually
going to see these very long COT traces, where
maybe the agent has opened a bunch of files, very
useful pre-training style data.
They take pull requests and then they
try to construct synthetic context for it,
using RAG that is potentially helpful for understanding
the pull request.
That all goes in the mid-training.
They will take documents that they detect using an automated
method to have text and code, and then they'll
use an LLM to transform this to a nice markdown format.
Throw that all in as well.
And then finally, they're going to have a language model talk
about coding on web documents that are coding-related
to generate coding-ish synthetic data,
and then they'll take publicly-available coding
agents, run them on various environments,
which I'll describe later.
And the traces of those runs all go into mid-training.
They'll do some fairly standard stuff as well,
like instruction following, and they'll
have an additional task, which I think
is not super relevant for us for filling in the middle.
If you're coding and you want to fill in the middle of a span,
it's useful to have that ability.
So they throw some of that data into mid-training.
But otherwise, this is a very standard but in-depth data
collection procedure to try to get
some of these agentic abilities into mid-training.
And then the Qwen folks do something
that I don't know if I've seen before.
It's actually quite interesting.
They'll take the mid-trained Qwen3 next model,
and they are actually just going to train
a whole bunch of different expert models
for different kinds of coding-adjacent tasks.
And they will end up with four different agent experts,
and then they're just going to distill them
all back into the same model.
I can only speculate as to why they do this.
I don't think I've seen it in other works.
The closest one I know of is DeepSeek V3, or was it V3?
V3.5, sorry, DeepSeek V3.5 or 3.2.
Maybe 3.2.
Sorry, 3.2, I think, did this thing
where they have different experts whose only job it
is to format and process data, so they
have data processing experts which generate
the data for the full training.
But I don't think I've seen this thing
of generating different model experts
and then distilling them back.
That's actually closer to some academic work like branch train
merge and so on.
Those are definitely things people do.
I haven't seen it much in frontier model training.
That said, each of these experts is actually interesting,
and what they do is they basically
do full-on RL and/or SFT training
on a whole bunch of different subtasks that they've defined.
So they have a web dev expert, where
they SFT on valid web code based on different kinds of checks.
They'll do things build UX experts
trained on many different tool formats, and they'll have QA.
So the QA agent is just trained on more synthetic data for code.
But then maybe the most interesting for us
and the most involved is their software engineering agent.
And what they do is they construct agent environments
at scale.
So SWE-bench is the gold standard
of these kinds of things.
And so what they want to do is they want SWE-bench but more.
They go out and they have various automated ways
based on GitHub to generate a ton of different issues.
And given this, they want to basically do
RL on these environments in some ways very unsurprising.
And what do they get?
They can get RL performance to go up.
One thing I will say here, and this is very important through the broader context of what we're
talking about, the reason why we can put more and more compute
into RL is because we believe that our reward
models are unhackable or difficult to hack.
If that assumption breaks down, your RL method
will find increasingly obscure ways of cheating you out
of your performance.
And so they have this great plot of basically, in Git,
you can look at future commits or different commits.
And if you have an issue and there's future commits,
you can just look up what the fix was.
And this is a very easy hack for models to learn.
And so they basically have a whole reward
whose entire purpose it is to prevent the agent from messing
with the Git history.
And if you don't do this, you end up
with a plot that looks like the right,
where it's learning, learning, learning, learning, learning.
And suddenly, you get this emergent jump, where
the emergent jump was actually, it
learned how to manipulate the Git calls to get the history.
And in some cases, it can even hack around certain constraints
you give it.
If you tell it, you can't use Git log,
it might add an origin like a remote and then query
the remote for what happened in certain commits.
So there's all sorts of hacking you can do.
RLVR is only as robust as your reward,
and your rewards can sometimes be not very robust at all.
As a side comment, one of my students and I
were working on a project that was like RL on Lean.
Lean is this formal math, verifiable language.
And we naively thought at the time,
there's no way this can go wrong.
Lots of people have worked on Lean.
The Lean compiler is bulletproof.
Turns out the Lean compiler is not adversarially robust.
There are strings that you can put
in it that will allow you to verify
proofs that are not meant to be verified in certain modes.
So I think the notion of verifiable rewards
is actually much trickier than many of you
might initially think.
Regardless, you do this process of constructing these GitHub
repos at scale.
You go through this process of doing RL,
you see your scores go up slow but steady, and in the end,
you will actually end up getting a system that is surprisingly
good, a model that achieves something
like 70.6% on SWE-bench, even though you have
what is basically a really tiny model, a three billion
active parameter model, you're able to do surprisingly
well on these tasks.
In some ways, though, I don't know
if this is super surprising.
RL, of course, you're going to be
able to do well on the environments for which you've trained.
You might even get generalization
to your validation set as you do here.
But you always want to be a little bit careful
about comparing performances.
Task-specific performance doesn't necessarily
mean it'll generalize to broader domains.
OK.
So that's basically all I've got for the RLVR lecture.
Remember the core takeaways of this lecture
is it's really all about the reward for RL.
RLHF and RLVR arguably they're very similar problems.
But with the difference being really just
we want more unhackable rewards so that we can actually
put in much more compute and get these systems to be much better.
GRPO, at least for the research community,
is something that really enabled a lot of this.
And you should all know GRPO very well.
You should know what the functional form is
and how the updates are.
This is something that you should know
as well just pre-training losses.
And then finally, at this point, I think lots of people
know how to do RLVR.
As you will find out, unfortunately, RL
remains very finicky and noisy and it's painful to work with.
But it's not that hard.
It's not like the old days of doing PPO on various really
tricky environments.
It's actually a lot smoother than you might think.
I'll stop here for a moment and take any final questions
before I let you all go, in case anyone has questions.
A really quick question-- when you
mention about the models being in thinking mode on and off,
is the wait on the model or [INAUDIBLE] the same?
Or do they play prompting or do they have different underlying
models that they call back?
Yeah.
So the question was about thinking mode
and what's happening on the back.
So the interesting thing about thinking mode really
is that it's actually one model.
And there's just a little prompt tag
that switches them between long and short, like long COT
and no coat almost mode.
Whereas if you just had an API flag or something, that's
not very difficult. The fact that
they were putting both of them in together
is the interesting bit there.
So you can actually choose, [INAUDIBLE]
but then you add extra prompt yourself to do COT?
Yeah, or the control mechanism in this case is in the prompt
rather than at the API or serving layer or something
like that.
Yeah.
Great.
Oh, yeah.
So you mentioned the phase of mid-training.
I was wondering how much of the formatting that
goes into the mid-training process,
informs what is able to be learned during the RLVR post-
training, and then as a secondary to that question of if you don't
have the correct data in mid-training,
then is it safe to assume that the reinforcement learning can't
sample a correct solution and therefore you can't learn it?
Yeah.
So the question was about the role of mid-training in RL.
I think there are a lot of empirical subtleties here.
I don't have a one-size-fits-all
answer. It will definitely not work as an answer,
but to give a little bit of the nuance,
I think pre-training and SFT are doing
a lot of the heavy lifting.
As long as you have coverage, if pre-training just
doesn't have any code data, then you're in trouble.
You need training.
But if your pre-training was very diverse and it covered,
let's go back to the mid-training slide.
If it covered a lot of stuff like text, code data
and it covered a bunch of GitHub data,
then this is very nice to have, but maybe not critical
because you're going to SFT anyway,
and the SFT will allow you to get close enough to start
getting some rewards for RL.
If you didn't have SFT, then you're in DeepSeek trouble.
But the fact that we're always going
to be doing some amount of SFT pre-RL really helps you,
and pre-training has enough coverage,
hopefully, that you're able to get
some reasonable generalization.
So mid-training is very nice to have.
Very important in order to get slightly better generalization,
but not necessarily make or break, I think.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE] there is a step after training your reward model.
We're going to still end up with a single model at the end.
So how does this kind of distillation work?
Do you have to design a mixed procedure?
Yeah.
So that's right.
So the distillation procedure is going
to require you to write down a sequence of prompts
on which the experts will be distilled into the final model.
Yeah.
I can definitely see the advantages
of this approach, which is that you
can have a separate team working on each expert.
It's much easier to have teams work on this.
And then the aggregation could potentially be simple as well
if you have enough compute.
It's just that this— if you have all the objectives,
you might as well just throw it into the big training loop.
Usually, I think that's how you would prefer to do things.
That way, you don't have to deal with this distillation
complication.
You could just have one big training objective that you then
do one training loop.
Yeah.
Is the long reasoning training also part
of the training, that mid-training?
So the question was, is the long reasoning training
part of mid-training.
So I think there's long COT SFT in both R1 and Kimi K5.1.
Long COT is not traditionally part of mid-training, per se,
but it is often—
long COT-like data is used in long context extension.
So it's a little bit more subtle.
I didn't talk about long context extension at all
and I regret that.
But usually, that's an additional phase right
before RLHF or other things, in this case,
also long COT, where you extend the context using
any long context data you have.
Usually, it's a combination of books, code, synthetic data,
because those are the things that are long enough
to do extension on.
So like I guess related to this diagram that's currently up,
when you're doing this [INAUDIBLE] process,
let's say how much math, chemistry, many other domains.
Is it common to do it in parallel, with one,
I guess, like reinforcement learning training run?
Or you do it sequentially?
And if you do it sequentially, how
do you avoid forgetting earlier parts of the learning?
Yeah, I think the closest answer to this question
do you do things sequentially or in parallel
is these diagrams, where the two splits that you
do is you split amongst like reasoning
problems and non-reasoning problems,
and the reasoning problems all go in one bucket
and they get executed at stage II.
And then the non-reasoning problems
happen at the final RLHF phase.
And this includes stuff like chattiness
and so on and so forth.
And those all go into the one later bit,
which is the stage IV.
See you next week.
[APPLAUSE]